Leah: Learning to cope with stress can
require some trial and error and what
works for one, might not work for another.
Childhood stress can be present in
any setting that requires the child
or young person to adapt or change.
Lots of children and young
people face ongoing challenges
they can’t quickly resolve, fear
kicks in, they get overwhelmed,
and they try to escape from it.
Rhiannon: Bad stress happens when
a threatening situation goes on and
on, and that can erode confidence
and may seem overwhelming.
The level of stress they feel
depends on past experience.
Leah: Not all stress is bad
however, there’s ‘good stress’, too.
Good stress is the type of stress
that accompanies excitement.
The pulse quickens and adrenaline
increases, even though there is no
threat or fear such as experienced
when riding a roller coaster.
Rhiannon: Stress may be caused by positive
changes, such as starting a new activity.
Stress is more likely to result in
positive outcomes if it is seen as a
challenge or something to strive to
overcome and therefore can help motivate.
When a child or young person confronts
a challenging situation and they feel
they can manage or control it, it gives
them confidence and makes them stronger,
ready to take on new challenges.
Leah: Ongoing challenges and fears can
create stress in children and young
people, but remembering past successes,
can help a child feel more in control.
This can help children and young
people rise to challenges such
as in sport or resolve problems
and build confidence in life.
Rhiannon: The body’s ability to deal
with stress can get the brain and
body ready to solve problems, and
kick into ‘fight or flight’ mode.
Dealing with danger quickly, can help
people to feel safe again, and when the
problem is overcome, the brain ‘feels
good’ more confident and resilient.
Leah: Confident and resilient individuals
see stress as a challenge that they can
and will master, and maybe even enjoy.
If they do, their success will
carry over to the next challenge.
Rhiannon: When children and young
people have support, and learn how to
support themselves when handling stress,
they’re better equipped to handle
challenges life may throw at them.
The more success they have, the more
confident and in-control they’ll feel,
then when they are feeling that success,
they are less likely to experience
and dwell on the bad forms of stress.